♪
｢There was a hungry crow｣
｢Who wanted to get some feed｣
♪
｢If only this beak were a little longer｣
｢That feed would be a bit closer｣
♪
～
｢A crow can think｣
♪
｢can think... can think｣
(
斎藤
)観察し
仮
説を立て
実験をし 考察する｡
Observe, propose a hypothesis, then experiment and consider results.
科学の考え方を学べ｡
Learn the way of scientific thought.
(山本)まずは ｢考える観察｣から｡
We begin with a Thinking Observation
この水そう すなの所を
よく見ると
→
Look closely at the sand in this aquarium.
しましまに なっている｡
It's all stripey.
３つの色に分かれて
地層
みたいな｡
It's separated into three colors, like geological strata.
なんで 色が 分かれているのか？
Why is it separated into these colors?
次の朝 見ると…
→
If we look at it the next morning...
しまが 無くなっている｡
The stripes are gone.
すなが １色に
なっている｡
The sand is all a uniform color.
どういう事なのか？
What's going on here?
さらに 時間を おいてみる｡
Let's try looking at it at the original time.
夜に見ると
また ３色に分かれている｡
If we look at it at night again we see the sand separated into 3 colors.
夜になると 出てくるものなのか？
It only comes out at night?
試しに すなを いじってみる｡
As a test, let's poke the sand.
うん？ すなを
動かすと…｡
Hunh? When we move the sand...
下の層も いっしょに動く｡
the layers underneath move with it.
もり上げると
下の層も もり上がる｡
If we pile it up, the layers underneath also pile up.
なんで こうなるのか？
Why should this be?
しばらく 観察してみる｡
Let's try observing for a little while.
あっ ﾔﾄﾞｶﾘの下に 何かが見える｡
Ahh. We can see somethig beneath the hermit crab.
何か かげのようなものが
→
Something like a shadow.
下の層に うつっている｡
is being cast on the lower layers.
これは かげなのか？
Is this some kind of shadow?
ﾋﾟﾝｾｯﾄでも 試してみる｡
Let's try testing with a pair of tweezers.
水に しずめると
→
When we lower it into the water
やはり
かげのようなものが うつる｡
as we thought, something like a shadow is cast.
かげ という事は
→
This shadow like thing
この 水そうを 照らしている
ﾗｲﾄが 関係しているのか？
might it have something to do with the light illuminating the aquarium?
ﾗｲﾄを 消してみる｡
Let's try turnig the light off.
しまが 消えた｡
The stripes disappeared.
ﾗｲﾄを 動かしてみる｡
Let's try moving the light.
しまが 動いた｡
The stripes moved.
やはり この ﾗｲﾄでできる かげが
しましまの正体らしい｡
As we thought, this light is the true cause of the stripes.
でも よく考えると
ちょっと 変だ｡
But as we think further it seems a bit strange.
このﾗｲﾄが
このﾋﾟﾝｾｯﾄを 照らしている時
→
When the light shines on these tweezers
かげは この つくえの上にだけ
出るはずだ｡
The shadow ought only be cast onto this desk.
なのに なんで こんな所に
かげが できているのか？
and yet somehow a shadow appears in the sand?
♪
～
(水が はねる音)
♪
～
(
蒼井
)今日は この 三角形の台と
鉄の玉を 使った問題です｡
Today's problem deals with this triangular stand and a ball bearing.
この三角形の台は
はかりの上に のっています｡
This triangular stand is placed on a scale.
台には ﾚｰﾙが付いています｡
There's a rail attached to this stand.
ﾚｰﾙの 上の部分には
ﾃｰﾌﾟが 付いていて
→
There's a little tape attached at the top of the rail.
玉が はり付き 止まります｡
firmly fixing the ball in place.
ここに 玉を のせると…｡
When the ball is sitting there...
200ｸﾞﾗﾑ ちょうど｡
it's exactly 200 grams.
鉄の玉と 台を合わせた重さです｡
The weight of the ball and the stand together.
ここからが 問題です｡
Now this is the problem.
しばらくすると
玉が ﾃｰﾌﾟから 自然に はがれ
→
A short time later the ball will come off the tape
転がり始めます｡
it will begin rolling.
玉が この坂を 転がってる間
→
While the ball is rolling down this incline
はかりが しめす数字は
どうなるでしょうか？
what will happen to the displayed weight?
さてさて どうなるか？
Well, what will happen?
答えは 番組の最後に 発表します｡
We'll present the answer at the end of the program.
みなさん
よ～く 考えておいてくださいね｡
Everyone, please think hard about it, won't you?
♪
～
観察 仮説 実験
そして 考察｡
Observation, hypothesis, experiment and reflection.
科学の考え方 ｢考えるｶﾗｽ｣｡
Thinking scientifically. Thinking Crow.
♪
～
では 先ほどの答えです｡
And now the answer from earlier.
みなさん ちゃんと考えましたか？
Everyone, did you think about it carefully?
では 実さいに
やってみましょう｡
Then, let's try it for real.
玉を ﾃｰﾌﾟに付けて
手を 放します｡
We affix the ball to the tape and remove our hands.
あとは ﾃｰﾌﾟから 自然に
はがれて
玉が 転がるのを待ちます｡
We wait for the ball to come free from the tape on its own and start rolling.
わたしが
少し さわっただけでも
→
Because if I touched it even a small amount
はかりの数字が
変わってしまうからです｡
the indicated weight would easily change.
さて 重さは どうなるか？
Well then, what will to the weight?
はかりの数字を
見ておいてくださいね｡
Please look closely at the weight shown on the scale, please.
♪
～
わかりましたか？
Did it change?
もう一度 見てみましょう｡
Let's look at that one more time
♪
～
という事で 答えは…
Then the answer...
どうしてでしょう？
Why do you think this is?
ﾃｰﾌﾟで とめられている時
→
When the ball is held by the tape...
玉の重さは 全部
この台に かかっていますよね｡
The weight of the ball is entirely contributed to this stand.
でも 玉が 転がっている間は…｡
But when the ball is rolling...
ここから先は 自分で考えよう｡
From here on we think for ourselves.
これからは みんなが｢考えるｶﾗｽ｣｡
From here on we're all thinking crows.